<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Something in plainess delivered to the beloved seed, as it bubled, or rise up through the earthen vessel</title>
            <author>M. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830666</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35119</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63710)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35119)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2080:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Something in plainess delivered to the beloved seed, as it bubled, or rise up through the earthen vessel</title>
                  <author>M. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1]  p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 7: M.T.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes a final postscript page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35119:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Something in plaineſs delivered to the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Seed, as it bubled, or riſe up through the earthen Veſſel.</head>
            <p>NOw that which I long to ſee brought forth in this Nation is, that man may be one with the Lord in his word, and Chriſt to be heard in all things, whom God hath appointed, and not to leave undone what he commandeth, neither to act before he be heard, but to be ſtill in their minds untill they hear him, then there would be no jealouſies, fears, nor controverſies, for God is not the Author of confuſion but of peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints. And I am for unity, peace and Order, and not diſorder, but it muſt be the Order of God, who doth all things both in heaven and in earth, according to the counſel of his own wiſe heart, and brings all things into peace and good Order, out of diſcord, where confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is. The Myſtery of Faith is held in a pure conſcience, void of offence towards God and man, And the Unity of the Spirit ſtands not in any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal thing, for that unity which ſtands ſo, their love will ebb and flow, which the ſpirit will break again, but the unity of the Spirit is a inviolable, unalterable, that which ſtands in the will, is ſoon broken, becauſe the will is brittle, and is peeviſh and froward if it hath not its end, now the ſeed can be content to leave it unto God, which cryeth, not my will but thy will be done. And that there might be an univerſal love towards all, if there be but a deſire or breathing after the life of innocency, and the life of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and wherein that they cannot come to us, that we may come to them, where the thing is not ſinful, but to abſtain from all appearance of evil: So therein ſhall we be as Saviours unto them, to judge the evil but love the good, and to bear the Ceremonies, or outward geſtures, to reach unto the tender ſeed, yea to be one with them, ſo far as not to ſin againſt God, till that be reached which is to be every ones Guide, Commander and Leader. And this the Lord hath opened unto me, that there might be an open way to come at the ſeed to reach the witneſs, in things that are nothing a Ceremonie or Circumſtance in all theſe things to come unto people; to ſpeak through them, as moved to the witneſs, keeping to the inviſible power and heeding of that, wherein God is able to deliver and preſerve,
<pb facs="tcp:35119:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35119:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35119:3"/>and to awaken them therein again that are there fallen a ſleep, or do not ſee beyond the viſible ſigne, by hearing the living voice, whenſoever he ſhall ſpeak, And this is ſtill in the way of God, ſo far as it is diſcovered by the light, for whatſoever maketh manifeſt is light, wherein the Lord will keep the ſincere hearted ſoul, which deſires no name in the Earth, but is will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be accounted any thing, or nothing, ſo that Gods holy name and power may be exalted over all in every heart, and the creature abaſed low before him. As it is written
<q>Tell the daughter of Zion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Behold thy King cometh unto thee meek, and ſitting upon an Aſs, and a colt, the foal of an Aſs, though it be ſmitten on all hands, yet it bears it all and ſuffers it, although it be ſmitten in the houſe of its friends, it grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, nor repineth: And note what was affected at that time, when he came in ſuch a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or low deſpicable manner into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he driveth the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple. For verily it is not a profeſſion only or name ſhall live, but that which is of the nature, and hath of the image of God upon it, whatſoever is of man ſhall fall but that which is of God ſhall ſtand. Do you ſee any run out as you think in their imaginations, bear with it a whiſe, and pray unto the Lord for the exalting his truth or what may be his mind or will, if the thing they ſpeak or do, be of man it will come to nothing, but if it be of God it will ſtand, that none may be found fighters againſt God in this day of his appeareance, as others have done in ages paſt under the name of hereticks, bad ſpirits, or ſciſmaticks, and what not? Much I have had at times of this kind opened in me, which if the Lord draw me forth, and there be an ear to receive it, I may the more freely come forth, for the days are evil, and I deſire to walk circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, and not to give any juſt offence to any one, but I cannot call good evil, nor evil good, nor put darkneſs for light, nor light for darkneſs, but what I have ſeen and felt, that I do declare, if any receive my teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, ſo, if not I ſhall not be angry with them, but leave it to the Lord who judgeth in righteouſneſs but this know, to be one with the Lord in his Work and know the mind of the ſpirit, to be of the ſpirits mind, therein is life and peace, in it, but not out of it. For I do not find the ſpirit place<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much the ſafety or proſperity or, the ſtanding of any man in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of people or ſociety without him, as in the faith within: As to ſay there is no ſtanding for any out of the body of friends. And another writing ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe that out of the body there was no proſperity, or they could not proſper: When as the Apoſtle declareth by faith ye ſtand. And <hi>David</hi> ſaith bleſſed is the man he doth not ſpeak of a Company, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35119:3"/>multitude that walketh not in the counſel of the ungodly nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners, nor ſitteth in the ſeat of the ſcornful, but his delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night, and he ſhall be like a tree planted by the rivers of water that brings forth his fruit in his ſeaſon, and whatſoever he doth, ſhall proſper, his leafe alſo ſhall not wither: Upon hearing or reading of thoſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions before mentioned it was brought to my remembrance the ſtate of the holy men of old <hi>Noah</hi> was a preacher of righteouſneſs in his Generation, and <hi>Noah</hi> walked with God, and we do not read of any other was with him, except his own Family, yet God ſaved him, and commanded him to come and all his houſe into the Ark, ſaying thee have I ſeen righteous before me in this Generation, whoſe eyes run to and fro throughout the whole earth ſtill. And <hi>Enoch</hi> in his day he walked with God, and ſo doubtleſs was in a ſafe ſtate; and what ſhall I ſay of <hi>Abraham</hi> in his day, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him and bleſt him, and <hi>Daniel</hi> in the captivity, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet the Lord was with him, though he was alone; and though I am alone in this matter whereof I write, yet I believe the Lord is with me and bleſſeth me, So bleſſed is the man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith <hi>EXTRA ECCLESIAM, NON EST SALUS,</hi> That is, Out of the Church is no Salvation, and tell people they muſt believe as the Church believeth, but Chriſt was before their Church or <hi>Rome</hi> either, and he ſaith learn of me, and believe in the light that ye may be children of the light. And the holy men of God were and are ſaved by their own Faith, and not by others, that is implicite Faith, but the Faith that Chriſt is the Author of in me, that is the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith that I am to cleave unto for Salvation, and not other mens though they be of the ſame Faith, yet their oyle will not ſerve me, I muſt have it in my own lamp or veſſel. And if that be thrown down which formerly was built up, and I have not faith in the thing, I do not know that I am a tranſgreſſour; Circumciſion is nothing nor uncircumciſion, but the keeping of the Commands of God, and the new creature avaiſeth the other is nothing, any outward viſible thing, though the life and power of God once appeared therein, and brings it not up again, but draws off from it, yet if he doth appear therein, it is but an external ſign, ſhadow or form, which is no farther to be heeded then as bowed thereunto by the Spirit; as kneeling is a ſigne or token of reverence, and the putting off the hat a ſigne or coken of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, but not the thing it ſelf or ſubſtance; the humility of Spirit is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35119:4"/>all, and that ſoul that yeilds obedience daily to what it knows, or is of God made manifeſt to it, is in the fear and is in the reverence, in the ſubſtantial part, of what the other repreſents. And this is not ſelf exaltation or being of <hi>Corahs</hi> ſpirit, to obey the Lord and keep his commandments and the evil way to hate and the forward mouth, for thoſe that honour the Lord he will honour and exalt them above their oppoſers. And it is Gods prerogative to change or alter, ſet up or pluck down at his pleaſure, that none may reſt in any thing ſhort of the ſubſtance or life it ſelf of the thing, and whatſoever a man doth, it is his part to do it believingly, and in that he pleaſeth God. And as I keep to the thing that maketh new, or the new creature I ſhall not plead for, or againſt any of the Signes or ſhadows among the Chriſtians, more then among the Jews, any further then the Spirit in newneſs induceth me, for this is the all to come unto Chriſt all and in all, then I am nothing, neither is the creature to be any thing in it ſelf, if Chriſt be all, then the ſhadows muſt fall, where the ſubſtance is enjoyed; If he be all in the Jew and Gentile, then he is to be looked at, and not the ſignes nor the ſhadows, and his permiſſion or command who ſuffers things to be, and doth all things in heaven and in earth according to his own good will and pleaſure, onely he asketh the heart, a willing and obedient heart and here is the one thing neceſſary, many things are not neceſſary but cumberſome and burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</p>
            <p>And that of the Apoſtle, he could not ſtand its like in the ſame exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal form to the Jews as he did to the Gentiles, nor to the Gentiles, as he did to the Jews, to pleaſe them, but one might have been diſpleaſed, but his condiſcention took off any occaſion of offence, he became all things that he might gain ſome, and yet the man the ſame as to God-ward giving none offence leaſt the Goſpel ſhould be evil ſpoken off, for the power would cruſh down that which would take offence, ſo was hereby the better able to come within them to reach to his own, or to the Word in them which he ſaid he preached, which word all people muſt hear that will live. The Word that ſhall live for ever, but the ſignes or the ſhadows, or the form wherein God once appeared he doth not ſay that ſhall live for ever. And it would be to little purpoſe for any to ſtrive to perpetuate a thing which will wear out as if there were any validity or worth in that to make them the better Chriſtians, it is the new heavens and the new Earth wherein righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs dweleth that remaineth, or is to remain, the other will wax old as a Garment, or that which man in the old nature is pleading for it is the new that remaineth; and it is in the newneſs of Spirit we are to ſerve him, who is our life our ſtreugth our daily preſerver, and it is by or through the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35119:4"/>renewings of the holy Ghoſt, whereby we are ſaved, through which the birth born of the ſpirit comes to live, the new birth without which it can neither live nor grow up.</p>
            <p>So I queſtioned with them, to wit the Papiſts, how were they ſafe where uncleanneſs unrighteouſneſs and drunkenneſs was, for that is ſhut out of the Kingdome. And ſo where there is reſpect of Perſons, height of ſpirit, haughtineſs or wiſe in their own conceit, how can there be ſafety or proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity. which would confine the Lord, or lye him as it were, to a taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, or certain number of men whom the heaven of heavens cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain? and ſuch onely to be righteous, when as the Apoſtle ſaith, be not wiſe in your own conceits but condeſcend to men of low eſtate, and in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted of him. So that thoſe that would limit the holy one or confine him to a tabernacle, and that there muſt be ſafety among ſuch and no more, may it not be juſt with the holy Lord God to leave them, and pitch his tent among others u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally, that it may appear there is ſafety where he wil be or manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he did his tabernacle which he planted in <hi>Shilo?</hi> and the Lord is come down to men of every Nation, in all profeſſions that fear him and work righteouſneſs, that his people may come down more to them in the ſigns and ſhadows, not for the ſhadows ſake, but for the ſeed ſake, and the Lords ſake who hath viſited them. And this to be ſure, amongſt all where there is moſt of the true knowledg and true learning, there will be moſt of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility meekneſs and love, Chriſt is a pattern and example to us, who hath ſaid as I have kept my Fathers Commandment and abide in his love, ſo ſhall ye abide in my love, if ye keep my commandments, who was obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſs, that is in doing the will of his Father, whoſe love is ſuch that it paſſeth knowledg, ſhould man then be ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his love, who hath vouchſafed to condeſcend unto mankind in their low condition, and not rejected them? whoſe tender mercies are over all his works. And ſo whom the Lord owns I may own, and every one may own, as being one with him in ſpirit, for he that is joined to the Lord is one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Saints had the mind of Chriſt, and not to leave or forſake any, becauſe of ſuch a profeſſion, but to have unity with the good, the plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, honeſty ſincerity and uprightneſs in them, and to bear teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the evil (as moved of the Lord) in them or what people ſoever, and ſo to be for the Lord, and neither for the one or the other people, no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the ſpirit unites or enjoyns. For the gathering is unto the Lord, the whole ſtock or race of mankind, into one entire body, life, love ſpirit and not for any to appropriate or arrogate to themſelves a priviledge above
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35119:5"/>others, ſeeing God is no reſpector of perſons, for if thou do well ſhalt thou not be accepted, if not, ſin lies at the door. And why may it not be as eaſic with God to keep man, or for a man or people to be kept entire and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle unto him in all or any profeſſion (that in themſelves are not ſinful) as for a man to be kept in the world trading buying and ſelling, for people in their worſhip (if at any time) their ſpirits are more bowed then at other times; and in a brotherly way I reaſon out things, and offer you my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in what I have received, if any know better or ſee further and that from the Lord I would willingly hear them, for men ſhould friendly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer together and offer one another their gifts and knowledg in love, and try things one with another, and hold that which is good, and friendly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct one another, and not ſo ſtand in their own opinion, as if they could not erre, ſeeing we have a mighty enemy againſt us, (the old Serpent the Devil) who ſuddenly brings ſtrange immaginations into mans thoughts, and maketh men inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; whence Sects and Sciſms exiſt, Was the ſaying of one, which I take notice of in this place. And all ſtrive in Religion or about the divine will whereby men deſpiſe one another cometh from ſelfiſhneſs; or ſelf immagination, that one man comprehendeth the image of another, <hi>viz.</hi> his thoughts and yet cannot rightly apprehend them; Where one man ſets himſelf in the thoughts and mind of another, and brings that which is his his own thereinto, and compelleth that which is anothers into his meaning and forcibly ſets himſelf aloft in the thoughts and mind of another, and holdeth them for his proper own, and will make a ſhew therewith, and there he domineers in and over the thoughts and minds of others. But a true man inclineth himſelf to his original (which is the word of God) and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh all images, and deſireth no ſelf imagining of his underſtanding, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what God will frame and ſpeak with and through him, and deſpiſeth none but onely diſtinguiſheth the true from the falſe the good from the evil, and teacheth the truth with divine and powerful out-flowings and will; for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in which truſted in themſelves and deſpiſed others, Chriſt gave forth a parable, two men went up to pray the one a <hi>Publican</hi> and the other a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> the <hi>Phariſee</hi> ſtood and juſtified himſelf, but the <hi>Publican</hi> ſtood afar off laying God be merciful unto me a ſinner, now here is Chriſts judgment of them, the latter went down to his houſe juſtified rather then the other, for every one that exalteth himſelf ſhal be abaſed and he that humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall be exalted. And ſpeaking further that the love of Chriſt groweth in the true life of man, and penetrateh through the life as fire doth through iron; Not that ſuch power ſtood in mans life, that it could receive the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God in its own power and vertue, No, it is given him of grace
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35119:5"/>(or introduced by Chriſt) as the Sun of its own will giveth it ſelf to the herb, and the herb cannot therefore ſay I am the ſun, becauſe the Sun worketh in it, ſo alſo can man not ſay I am Chriſt, becauſe that Chriſt dwelleth and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him, as in his expreſs image. But the Creature is the paſſive, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Creatot dwelleth and worketh for ſo as ſaith the Apoſtle we are all the ſons of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus. And here let me aſk a queſtion, Chriſt the ſeed of God being come up in male or female, then which is greateſt? or the holy birth being born, begotten with the word of truth? and ſo all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought one among another, where there is moſt of meekneſs love and humility there is moſt of God and moſt of Chriſt, and that will prevail, for it is not hardheartedneſs, falſe accuſing nor evil ſpeaking, or envie that ſhall prevail, neither is that ſtate ſafe or proſperous; for two men of two differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent forms the one hath enmity in his heart ariſing againſt another or hatred, when as the Apoſtle ſaith he that hates his brother is a murderer, and no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer hath eternal life, which thing is to be ſeen in the higheſt form; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a degree below him in profeſſion walks in humility of mind, honeſty and plain heartedneſs, whether of theſe two is to be united unto, or owned to be a friend, he is my neighbour that ſheweth compaſſion unto me, and that is my friend that doth me good, and not hurt. But the Lord is exalting his Son over all I verily believe, yet becauſe he cometh not in mans way or form therefore he cannot be received, the ſame that ever was, but happy are they that wait upon him in his own way in the light, and bleſſed is he who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall not be offended in the ſon; and this is another thing for us to mind, not ſo much to be eyeing man as the Lord in all his diſpenſations, for if the Supream or chief ruler of a Nation be made to afflict or bring a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under, not ſo much to look at him, as the hand that brings it to paſs, and then to rejoice when we fall into divers tryals; or if he ſhould favour a people or countenance them, then to keep low, and that Spirit is the creeping Spirit that creeps up high into pride and loftineſs one above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which came in when the fear of the Lord was not ſtood in, and the low watchful ſpirit as firſt appeared when fleſh was abaſed, and the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone exalted, which brought in a great ſtilneſs upon all fleſh, and ſilence, but now the loud and clamorous thing in many is apt to get up, which is not afraid to ſpeak evil. Remember the cloſure of the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children keep your ſelves from Idols, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>So the Lord God everlaſting open every underſtanding and keep all clear to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> 
               <signed>M.T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:35119:6"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THere is a generation thas calleth themſelves righteous and yet are not purged from their iniquity, but are apt to ſpeak evil of men calling them Ranters, and the like, which was the name the rude Multitude called at the firſt, And other ſuch unſavory ſpeeches. For am I ſo to ſpeak that nothing may proceed out of my mouth, but that which tends to ediſication, then to what ediſication is ſuch language as this? Did ever the ſpirit of the Lord call ſo? or the Scriptures bear Teſtimony of ſuch names? But ſaith indeed if they have called the Maſter of the houſe Belze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub, how much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold? But the Chriſt like ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will at laſt overturn theſe names and denominations, which doth good unto all, and ſpeaks evll of no man, nor upbraideth, and him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l call a Chriſtian, which ſpeaks and acts according as the ſpirit of Chriſt putteth it ſelf forth in him, there is none a Chriſtian unleſs Christ lives and works in him, as himſelf ſaid, without me, you can do nothing: and all gatherings out of this ſpirit will be ſcattered abroad and come to nothing; therefore happy are the people that have made the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their rock their fortreſs and their refuge, that have the bent of their ſpirits to Godward, in what they do.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35119:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
